Guide to the Chris Costner Sizemore Papers, 1952-1989 (bulk 1956-1979) RL.01198
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Chris Costner Sizemore papers
1952-1989 (bulk 1956-1979)
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Sizemore, Chris Costner
RL.01198
8 Linear Feet
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Provenance
The papers of Chris Costner Sizemore were acquired by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library from 1982 through 1989.
Biographical Note
Chronology
1927 Apr 4 Born in Edgefield, S.C. to Acie and Zueline Hastings Costner.
1929 Traumas witnessed. First memory of additional personalities: the Red Head Girl, Ugly Girl, and Black Patent Shoe Girl.
1933 Twin sisters, Elyse and Louise, born.
1946 Married George Rodgers.
1948 Daughter Taffy born.
1952 Divorced George Rodgers. Multiple personality disorder diagnosed by Dr. Corbett Thigpen and Dr. Hervey Cleckley.
1953 Married Don Sizemore.
1957 McGraw-Hill released The Three Faces of Eve by Corbett Thigpen. Film version came out the same year.
1958 Co-authored The Final Face of Eve with James Poling.
1959 Son, Bobby Sizemore, born.
1974 Illness resolved.
1975 Began lecturing.
1977 Doubleday released I'm Eve, by Sizemore and cousin Elen Sain Pittillo.
Collection Overview
The Chris Costner Sizemore Papers span the time period 1952-1989, with the bulk of the papers dating between 1956 and 1979. The collection consists largely of correspondence; diaries and writings by Sizemore; publicity centered on film and book promotions or speaking engagements; materials related to her appearances; interviews and documentary materials (including film, video- and audiocassettes); and assorted materials including photographs, legal and financial papers. Most items relate to Sizemore's struggle with multiple personality disorder (dissociative identity disorder), both personally through letters, writings, and diaries, and publicly through interviews, documentary media, and news clippings. The papers provide an in-depth look into the life of a woman with a rare disorder who later came to clearly articulate her life to the public and become a mental health advocate. A biography was written by her doctors in 1957, Corbett Thigpen and Hervey Cleckley, called The Three Faces of Eve. It was turned into a film the next year. Under the pseudonym, Evelyn Lancaster, Sizemore co-authored The Final Face of Eve with James Poling in 1958. In 1977 she wrote, under her given name, the autobiography I'm Eve. The Correspondence Series is arranged chronologically, and consists primarily of incoming letters. Dr. Corbett Thigpen, the doctor to deliver the original diagnosis of multiple personality disorder, is prominent in much of the collection. This series documents his relationship to Sizemore during treatment and continuing well into the 1970s. He corresponded with Sizemore about his writings, revealing much about the publication of The Three Faces of Eve (book), and its subsequent movie release. The series also contains correspondence with other doctors, family members, Sizemore's editors and publishers, and organizations for which she lectured. The Writings Series is comprised primarily of the holograph manuscript, typescript, final galley proofs, and paperback edition of I'm Eve, the memoir written by Sizemore with the help of Elen Pittillo. This comprehensive view of the book's publication is represented from handwritten copy to final edition. The Writings Series also includes some short descriptions of Sizemore's life and examples of her poetry, as well as a few writings by others. There are six diaries in the Diaries Series, kept during parts of the 1950s and 1970s. Within these volumes, Sizemore discloses inner thoughts, which reveal very personal information about enduring mental illness and its effects on her family. The Publicity Series includes news clippings and journal articles about Sizemore and multiple personality disorder, as well as media related to her published works. The Events Series contains materials and ephemera related to Sizemore's public life of art shows, lectures, broadcasts, and appearances, often for mental health organizations. It also contains materials from her book tour for The Three Faces of Eve. The Photographs Series contains pictures from these events and of Sizemore's family life. The Additional Materials Series contains financial and legal papers, medical files, and identifying documents. There is also an Audio Visual Materials Series that contains interviews and documentary materials that again reflect the public's interest in Sizemore's life, as well as her own desire to document and share her experiences in writing, speaking, and art. Included is a documentary film by Dr. Thigpen, and video and audiocassettes of television interviews, other appearances, and of family members discussing a shared past (sound quality of some of the audiocassettes is very poor).
Women -- Psychology -- Case studies; Women -- Mental health -- Personal narratives; Women -- Biography; Mental illness -- Personal narratives; Diaries -- Women authors; Women authors, American; Multiple personality -- United States -- Case studies; Multiple personality in art; Diaries; Sizemore, Chris Costner -- I'm Eve
- Correspondence Series, 1949-1982 and undated, 2 boxes
  Scope and Contents note
  Includes letters from Dr. Corbett H. Thigpen, other doctors, friends, family members, editors, publishers, and some who had recently seen Sizemore on television or read her works. Letters are arranged chronologically with undated letters at the end. Most attachments remain clipped to the individual letters, and so this particular series also includes some photographs, royalty statements, and other miscellaneous materials. A few additional items are housed in the oversize materials.
  - Personal
    - Dec.1949 - July 1974, 23 folders (Box 1)
    - July 1974 - Nov. 1977 (Box 2)
    - Dec.1977 - Dec. 1979 (Box 3)
    - Jan.1980 - April 1982 (Box 4)
    - March 1982 - Dec. 1983 and undated (Box 5)
  - Medical
    - Thigpen I, March 1956 - Dec. 1956 (Box 5)
    - Thigpen II, Jan. 1957 - Dec. 1957 (Box 5)
    - Thigpen III, April 1958 - March 1970 (Box 5)
    - Thigpen IV, Jan. 1972 - Feb. 1974 (Box 5)
    - Medical Correspondence (Box 12)
  - Written Works
    - Poling, Feb. 1957 - Nov. 1958 (Box 5)
    - Maclean's, July 1954 - Feb. 1957 (Box 5)
    - Regarding Three Faces of Eve (Box 12)
- Diaries Series, 1953-1975, 2 folders
  - Dec.1953 - Dec. 1957 (Box 7)
  - 1973, 2 vols. (Box 7)
  - June 1974 - May 1975 (Box 7)
- Writings Series, 1 box
  Includes typescripts of the publication I'm Eve, as well as poetry by Sizemore and others. See also Oversize Materials group.
  - I'm Eve - typescript, 6 folders (Box 6)
  - I'm Eve - paperback (Box 7)
  - Volumes - German (Box 7)
  - Miscellaneous writings by Sizemore and others, 2 folders (Box 7)
  - Notes written by "Jane," undated (Box 7)
  - I'm Eve - handwritten manuscript, 12 folders (Box 8)
  - I'm Eve - final galley proofs (Box 9)
  - Oversize Materials Group (Oversize-folder 1)
- Publicity Series
  - Clippings, July 1953 - Oct. 1986 and undated; 3 folders (Box 10)
  - Clippings - movie related (Box 10)
  - Printed materials (Box 10)
  - Press list (Box 10)
  - Articles about Sizemore and MP Disorder (Box 10)
  - Book jackets (Box 11)
  - Atlanta Journal and Constitution cover (Box 13)
  - George Mason University event poster (Box 13)
  - Oversize magazines (Box 13)
- Events Series
  - Guestbook - George Mason University, March 25 - April 15, 1980 (Box 10)
  - Student responses to Sizemore lectures (Box 10)
  - Penn. State film script (Box 10)
  - Lectures and guest talks- Book tour (Box 11)
  - Lectures and guest talks- Mental Health Association (Box 11)
  - Lectures and guest talks- Miscellaneous (Box 11)
  - Lectures and guest talks- Ephemera (Box 11)
  - Gifts and awards (Box 11)
  - Duke University, 1973 (Box 11)
- Photographs Series
  - Manuscripts department party, May 25, 1980 (Box 11)
  - Miscellaneous photographs (Box 11)
  - Oversize photographs (Box 13)
- Additional Materials Series, 2.5 boxes
  Conditions Governing Access
  Contents of this box restricted pending review.
  - Tax records, 1966 (Box 12)
  - Book contract, 1953 (Box 12)
  - Identifying documents, 2 folders (Box 12)
  - Medical information (Box 12)
  - Financial papers (Box 12)
  - Legal papers (Box 12)
- Audiovisual Materials Series, 1977-1989 and undated
  - Audio recordings
    - (A) South Carolina Medical Association Hearing regarding Sizemore's father (Box 15)
  - Interview recordings
    - (B) Patricia McCann Program, WOR-AM, 9 Jul. 1977,interview (Box 15)
    - (F) Family interviews
      It is likely that these were recorded by Sizemore and Pittilo in preparation for writing I'm Eve. Each tape is listed below with the first name found written on the master copy, although there may be more than one person interviewed on each tape. See Master Copy labels for more information.
      - (1) Tiny (Box 15)
      - (2) Becky (Box 15)
      - (3) Bobby (Box 15)
      - (4) Anne (Box 15)
      - (5) Aunt Mamie Lee (Box 15)
      - (6) Taffy (Box 15)
      - (7) Taffy (Box 15)
      - (8) Taffy (Box 15)
      - (9) Don (Box 15)
      - (10) Don (Box 15)
      - (11) Don (Box 15)
      - (12) Chris (Box 15)
      - (13) Maud Cogburn (Box 15)
      - (14) Jane (Box 15)
      - (15) Don (Box 15)
      - (16) Chris (Box 15)
      - (17) Chris (Box 15)
      - (18) Chris (Box 15)
      - (19) Chris (Box 15)
      - (20) Chris (Box 15)
  - Speaking engagements
    - (C) Unnamed speaking engagement (Box 15)
    - (D) "The Three Faces of Eve," readings and commentary, Corbett H. Thigpen (Box 15)
    - (E) "I'm Eve" radio spot (Box 15)
  - Film and video
    - Videotapes (Box 16)
      - Lecture for the Mental Health Association of Utah (Box 16)
      - Eve's Art, KHOU-TV, 7 Dec. 1978 (Box 16)
      - Morning Break/Chris Sizemore (Box 16)
      - Sunday Break, "Eve," 12 Mar. 1982 (Box 16)
      - Good Morning America, 28 Sept. 1989 (Box 16)
    - Film
      - What's Your Opinion?(1 reel) (Box 16)
      - Series on Sizemore (2 reels) (Box 16)
      - Case Study of Multiple Personality (1 reel) (Box 14)